There are a few things that I see people
do wrong that really break my heart when
it comes to selling their business. I'm
Sarah Sharp. I'm a deal attorney. I help
people buy and sell businesses every
day. And I specifically help people in
the accounting practice industry. And
this week, I've had a trend where I have
met with a number of sellers who were
not intending to sell, but there was an
unfortunate life event where they had
to. And you hear about that happening a
lot. And a lot of times it's from
somebody trying to sell you something
and um certainly that is something that
I have seen. But there's a lot of truth
to it too. I had some client calls with
people who had had really big deal
diagnosis where all of a sudden they had
to escalate and couldn't do a single
other tax season. And in that instance,
one of those happened. And I had another
deal where they had just gone under LOI.
But unfortunately, one of the owners had
come down with a terminal diagnosis and
that put the entire sale for all of the
other owners in jeopardy and probably
meant that instead of selling, they're
looking at having a 3 or 4 year
stabilization process before they will
even be able to have a firm that they
can sell. That is not ideal. And there's
not ever I don't think anyone who's
going to tell you that you shouldn't be
doing succession planning from day one.
But seeing it and going through it with
clients really hammers it home. So I
just want to tell you about the cycle of
a sale. And if you are running an
accounting practice right now, it is
never too soon to start looking into
what matters to a buyer because you can
start making those metrics exactly what
you want them to be. I know that you
might think that buyers only care about
the revenue. They don't. There's a lot
of folks who prioritize monthly
recurring revenue over any other kinds
of revenue. There are some buyers who
will not touch audit in a test work with
a 10-ft pole. There are fewer but
existing clients that will only touch
audit and the test. So, you may wish to
know what that looks like so that you
can modify your service mix and change
your hiring based on that. Also, if you
are willing to stick around for a while
as a seller, you will get a better price
than if you cannot or will not. So,
earlier is going to bring you more
money. And so, it's never too soon to
kind of dig in on that. I have had deals
where unfortunately one of many partners
but a very you know prominent good
service partner passes away unexpectedly
right before the tax deadline and the
entire partnership is left scrambling
which results in a pretty rocky looking
financial picture for a year which then
means you're looking at a next year to
stabilize. You have to explain it when
you go to sell and it's not as easy to
find somebody who's willing to take the
risk of the picture of super jumpy rocky
trailing 12 months. So you wind up with
a more conservative potential buyer. If
you are thinking about selling good plan
accordingly, get some youth on your
payroll if you can start training some
folks up so that if anything happens to
any of the owners, you've got somebody
who can step in and actually help. And
it will help your purchase price a great
deal if they see that there's some folks
who actually know what they're doing and
continuity who are not all exactly the
same age. I super regularly see deals
where every single person on the payroll
and the owners all came up together and
they're like a family and that's
wonderful, but they are all 75 years
old. Exactly. And that can be, you know,
its own type of trick to sell. There is
a reality that sellers always need to
confront upfront when they realize what
their firm is worth, which is there is
some amount of continuing to work they
could have done. You're talking in a
multiple of years. A lot of times people
will talk in a multiple of IBIDA, a
multiple of gross revenue, but really I
think they should be talking in a
multiple of years. So, if you have a $1
million firm for which you bring home
$400,000 a year and you're going to sell
it for a million, you could have just
worked for two and a half more years and
been better off financially with no risk
and then just thrown the keys into the
ravine, walked away, it explodes behind
you somehow in slow motion. There is
always a number for that. If you sold
that same firm for, you know, $5
million, there's still a number of
years. I don't know what it is. I'm not
a famous mathematician. There's still a
number of years that will equate to $5
million where you could have just
continued working making 400k a year and
been in the same or similar position.
That will always be the case. So, don't
take a second, don't take too long to
recognize what that is. You do not want
to put yourself in a situation where
you're halfway down the deal process
before you do the math on the fact that
you could have just kept working for a
year and a half and made the same amount
of money. I know that all of my clients
are accountants. They still have an
emotional block when it comes to doing
the math on that and making that
realization. So, if that's the fact, how
do you sell your business? Well, number
one is come to terms with the fact that
you could have kept working, made a lot
of money. That's just the fact. I have a
lot of people who I've interacted with
who were going to sell their firm, had
that realization, took it off the
market, said, "I'm just going to work
for two and a half more years." And
guess what? I see them in two and a half
years. And they have not thrown the keys
into the ravine because we are all
responsible business owners. And nobody
throws their keys into the ravine.
Eventually, you have to figure out how
to stop this business. This giant
machine that's continuously going won't
just stop on its own without, you know,
you getting sued for malpractice. So a
lot of times you have to figure out a
way to wind it down. And most of my
clients would prefer a sale to a trusted
person who's going to take care of their
clients and their employees. So even if
the math is true that you could have
worked for 2 and a half more years and
been in the same financial position, if
you just go ahead and do it now, you
won't find yourself doing the same math
with the same realization 2 and a half
years later and 2 and a half years after
that until you're 1,000 years old,
right? Eventually you have to call it.
But you also have to balance that math
of how long it would have taken you to
make the same amount of money as the
sale against how long you're willing to
run the business. Because most sellers
will want you to be partially engaged or
maybe most buyers will make want you to
be at least partially on the payroll or
continuing to work for one year. You'll
get way more if you're willing to stay
for 3 years. You'll get way more if
you're willing to stay for five. At what
point is the purchase price enough that
you can be working for three years and
still be better off than if you had just
not sold and worked for three years? So,
do the math on all the pieces, but I
recommend that you take a look at the
multiple that matters the most, which is
time. The one thing we don't get more of
in this world. So, how many years would
it have taken you to make the same
amount of money? And make your decisions
there. And don't wait until you're ready
to sell to get ready to sell. Do it now.
If this was helpful at all, check out
dealacademy.org. Like and subscribe with
the content. Sign up for my newsletter.
Um, email me or follow me on LinkedIn.